[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
org slash software hello this is Charles
Anderson for software engineering radio
today we're talking to John Thomas
author of the book soft skills John is a
software developer podcaster blogger
consultant entrepreneur YouTube host and
author
he is also retired by some definitions
of the world of the word although he's
still very busy John welcome to software
engineering radio is there anything else
you'd like to add to that Reese
background I think that that that mostly
covers it I guess I've got my hands on a
lot of different things you know I guess
I'd say that you know mostly what I am
today is it's just someone who wants to
help software developers to live better
lives to be better at their jobs and so
that's everything I do is based around
those those two goals okay great so
software engineering radio bills itself
as the podcast for professional software
developers and your book is a manual for
professional software developers
therefore it seemed to me to be a pretty
good fit for our audience but your book
is not really about code what is it
about so it's about it's actually about
all the non code things that I that I
think is you know and it's funny because
these aren't things that just software
developers deal with right these are
things that people deal with but but I
approach it from the software developer
just mindset and the software developer
you know as the the target person to
read this book but but soft skills
really is you know I think there's lots
of definitions for it and so a lot of
people would say okay well soft skills
that's people skills right and and to me
it's more than that it's what it is is
is exactly how you described it which is
everything that isn't code that that is
in your life it's anything that's a not
a hard skill not a technical skill but
it's a soft skill so that involves
people skill
but it also involves career management
you know how do you how do you climb the
ladder how do you manage your career are
you actually even thinking about these
things a lot of developers aren't it
even involves things like like
productivity or or finance or even
fitness you know these are all areas of
our life that that exists that we have
to have these skills and in order to be
successful and not just successful
financially not successfully just in our
career but to be successful in in the
terms of being a happy human being who
has it feels like they have a balanced
life and it enjoys what they do can get
the most out of life so that's really
where the what the book is focused on is
is taking kind of you know as you as you
described in the intro I've I've done a
lot of things I've been in a lot of
different places and and involved in a
lot of different things and I've kind of
tried to distill all that wisdom that
I've gathered from just from what I've
done and also from I've had the
privilege of talking to a lot of
millionaires and some billionaires and
very successful people in the software
development realm and other fitness and
other realms and gain their wisdom and
put that into that book so that's kind
of what the the idea and the goal of
that book is yeah
like you say I the the term soft skills
I was assuming was going to be
relationship stuff but it's a whole lot
more than that which was interesting to
me the book is grouped into seven
sections that provide a good outline of
the content you've kind of touched on a
couple of those could you go over those
for our audience sure so you know first
I start off with with career which is
basically like we talked about you know
how do you what are your goals how do
you manage your career how do you do
things like get a raise or you know how
do you think about where what kind of
company do you even want to work for
like have you even considered the
differences between the different kinds
of developers that there are different
types of companies and and how you know
how did how to best present yourself at
a job so then we get into the second
section which is marketing yourself
which is something that I've I'm really
big on I don't think there's hardly
anyone in the software development field
that talks about building a brand and
marketing yourself you know it kind of
gets a bad rap but I
defuse that and say look marketing is
just really about providing a value or
service to someone who's looking for
that and that's what we really should be
doing as a software developer so I
talked about how you can go out there
and build a brand create a blog you know
maybe even create your own podcasts or
be on podcasts get that out there so
that you you become a name in the
industry which is gonna it's gonna
benefit your career in your life in in
multiple ways then we get into really
productivity which you know productivity
is obviously a wide topic but I sort of
give my my methods and my ways of being
extremely productive at least what I
felt has been extremely productive as
you know in in in the last few years
I've been able to produce like 55
Pluralsight courses and dozens of blog
posts and just a lot of different
content and so I have a system for that
and I go over that and then I get into
learning which I've had to learn how to
learn I think a lot of developers a lot
of people in general don't really master
the skill they get used to going to
school and having someone tell them how
to learn or what to learn and so
figuring out how to learn things really
on their own so I dedicate a section
talking about you know an exact ten step
process that I've used as I've been
teaching par site courses and teaching
developers to be able to take something
and very quickly learn it and then and
then one of the key parts of that is to
teach it to someone else then we get
into the whole finance side which I'll
just briefly touch on but I think a lot
of a lot of software developers a lot of
people you know we use money every day
right our you know a lot of our career
choices and decisions are based on money
we're thinking about retirement but a
lot of people don't even understand how
a bank works you know and you know you
know it's nothing to be ashamed of but
but a majority of people out there
really don't understand how the
financial system and and and how money
actually works and and how it affects
their lives and so I think it's it's an
important thing to have that knowledge
same thing in the fitness side and
that's where where it goes next is I
think a lot of developers
realize how important health and fitness
is not just for living longer but for
feeling better for having confidence you
know really affects a lot of areas of
your life so I talked about that and
then finally I wrap it up with with the
section that I call spirit which is
basically you know I was trying to come
up with a good term for this but it's
basically sort of this would be the kind
of things that you might read in and I
don't like to use the term but self-help
books but things were you know the
mental aspect you know in order to be
really successful and well-rounded I
think there's a for an important part of
that is to have a positive attitude to
think about things the right way to be
able to master yourself to have
self-discipline and control your
emotions in your mind and to to really
that's the thing that really empowers
you and so I wrap up you know with that
and and that in my view is that's why I
call it the software developers life
manual is because it kind of covers all
areas of life there yeah it is it is
quite expansive and and like I said
before I did personally I didn't think
that the title soft skills did it
justice it seemed to be covering so much
but within each section you have
chapters and the chapters are quite
small and digestible it's almost like it
was a collection of blog postings what
was the origin of the book and if it
wasn't blog postings why did you go for
that structure so there's there's a few
different reasons that I went for that
structure one of them was you know I've
been blogging for a while and used to
write those shorter articles I did
actually derive a lot of the chapters
they're not copies of blog posts but
from ideas of popular blog post that I
wrote I kind of rehashed my thoughts on
on that so that's where kind of some of
that came from that's how I knew what
people are interested in and what what
topics to to discuss and also from
YouTube videos and things like that but
but really the primary motivation for
breaking it up like that is that I
thought about two things which is one
how I like to consume content like when
I'm reading a book what would be ideal
and for me you know
I do this all the time now you know I'll
be reading a book and I don't know if
you do this as well but um you know
you're if you're reading a physical book
like I'll scan ahead to try to find out
where the chapter ends because I I want
to end on the chapter you know because I
know you could just you know just put a
bookmark in but then I forget where I'm
at right I don't lose the context so I
want to finish on chapters and so what
ends up happening is I I reach for my
book or reach for my Kindle and I put it
back down because I'm like well I only
have five minutes so I'm not I'll wait
till I have half an hour to read and so
I wanted to create the book that you
could just grab you know when you have
five minutes and you can read a whole
chapter in five minutes and get a
complete thought and then and so you
could work your way through it I felt
like that's a an easier way to read in
and then the reader doesn't feel like
they're trying to get to the end because
they know that in fact when they get to
the end they're like oh that I wish
there were more in this chapter so
that's that's the feeling I wanted to
create and then also from a writing
perspective you know I wrote this book
in in probably about three months it's I
I broke it down into those pieces that
you know I can write a chapter a day and
writing a chapter at a is making solid
progress towards towards getting that
book and that's actually talked about it
in the productivity section in fact I
it's a little meta when I when I talk
about how I'm writing the book and
basically about setting a quota and a
goal for myself is okay every single day
I am going to write a chapter of this
book and so I know that there's 74
chapters in this book so in 74 days I
will have written that at least the
first draft of this book okay yeah that
makes perfect sense I appreciate smaller
more digestible chapters for exactly the
reasons you read you mentioned I
remember Scott Meyer as an effective C++
book was really good for that yeah
actually one of my favorite books of all
time by the way okay cool yeah it's been
a long time since I've I've read it so
we don't have time to go into all of the
sections of the book today but I wanted
to just focus on a couple of them the
first two that you mentioned career and
marketing you're yourself so in career
is there one area
career management that you think many
software developers could use help with
let's see so I would say for career
management the biggest the biggest thing
I would say is just having a goal like
knowing where you're going yeah and I
kind of start the book off really with
that because I think that is so
important I always draw this analogy to
you know a ship you know that sailing in
the ocean without without a destination
like you're gonna float you're gonna go
somewhere but you're who knows where
you're gonna go right but but when you
have a goal in mind when you have a
destination then you can you can you can
prop the sail and in a particular
direction and turns up the rudder in
order to be able to go that direction
then you're you're more likely that you
can use the wind to take you there and
so many developers I think today they
they just assume that you know in five
years they'll be in a better place but
they don't have it charted out they
don't know where they're gonna go they
don't really have solid goals so you
know it's and almost all areas of life I
found that's to be true that if you
actually set a goal especially if you
write it on paper or especially if you
you know take the actress step and you
you put it on paper and and put it
somewhere where you'll see it every
single day then you're so much more that
the chances of you achieving that goal
go up tremendously and then and then you
you get you get into this habit of
becoming someone who reaches close what
I call a finisher finishing things and
then pretty soon you're jumping to next
goal next goal and you know literally in
my life and once I started doing this
setting goals and actually achieving
them in in a in a two year period I
achieved more than I had in the previous
10 years just by by doing this Wow okay
yeah and Stephen Covey calls calls it
you know start with the end in mind
yeah certainly that's that's valuable
advice you cover pretty much all of the
work models for software developers from
regular employees to entrepreneurs
starting their own company on the show
here and episode 168 as I recall we
discussed contracting or consulting
actually
where do you see the profession of
software development headed is there a
work model that you think will change
become more dominant or anything so that
this is an interesting question you know
I've got an unpopular answer I know that
it's not popular because I did a blog
post on this and and and people didn't
like it but but I'm I'm here to tell the
truth and and where I honestly think
that we're going like just in general
the workforce in general is to an
entrepreneurial type of system I think
when you look at it from political
systems with minimum wages and
healthcare and requirements and things
like that burdens that that are
traditionally put on employers but
employers are kind of shirking often
saying well we don't want to do this and
and and when you when you have the
internet and you have you know things
like upwork and fiber and all these you
know ways to get contract services and
you've and we're getting more of a
global economy where even software
development is becoming commoditized to
some degree and you can you can hire
really good developers you know outside
of outside of the you know in
third-world countries I think we're
gonna get to this point where basically
you know the workforces is a majority of
entrepreneurs who are building their own
businesses who are working as
freelancers as providing services and
not just hourly you know there's a
difference I think between staff
augmentation which is where you hire
someone hourly and you tell them what to
do right and that's I mean it's it's I'm
not trying to disrespect that that's a
perfectly I did that for a long time but
there's a difference between that and
being the kind of hourly person who who
basically provides a service who is who
is billing for their time but they're
providing a specific server so we're
gonna package a productized service
where maybe I charge you $2,000 and I
build you a web site right so I think
that that's where we're gonna end up
going and I and I and I talked about
this also from the perspective of of me
having a business and me hiring people I
have one direct employee that's a
full-time employee and then I
have about nine contractors working for
me on a weekly basis that do things from
you know recording video and editing
video to editing podcast to managing my
content and doing editing on my blog
post to doing transcription right so I'm
already doing this model because it's
more efficient and effective for me
rather than having two or three
full-time employees that have to be
trained in multiple disciplines and and
and if one of them is sick then that
what do I do
so that's that's really where I see the
profession going and that's also why I'm
such a big proponent of marketing
yourself in building a brand because in
that world where at least where I see
the Softee Volant world going you have
to have a reputation you have to have a
brand because you have to set yourself
apart if you actually want to you know
get the business and so I think that's
you know that's what we can probably see
you know it's gonna take a while I think
there's still be traditional jobs you
know everyone you can put down the
pitchforks you know there's it but but
long-term guaranteed employment is
something that you it it belonged to our
fatherís age and our grandfathers but
it's it's no longer guarantee in the
world that we live in and and I don't
see that trend reversing okay you set us
up for the marketing which we'll get to
in a bit let's stick with career for a
little bit so you recommend that
software developers have a
specialization to avoid being a jack of
all trades and a master of none on the
other hand I'm personally suspicious a
very narrow-minded over specialization
can you elaborate on where you think
that sweet spot is sure so there's some
there's there's a few different ways
I've seen this described I mean probably
the most popular one that I probably
agree with is a t-shaped model which is
basically where you have a broad base
and then you have a very narrow
specialization so that's where you get
the tea where you deeply know know
something I don't talk about the
t-shaped model all that much because I
think that in order to get a deep
knowledge of something you have to build
a broad base
it's just it's too hard to to get far
enough deep down the chain without
encountering a whole bunch of other
things as well so in and I in in and I
think that there's more resistance you
know I'm always an extremist so I'm
always trying to push really hard in the
direction that people don't want to go
maybe a little bit harder than you need
to go just because of the the resistance
to make sure that people go that
direction so so when I say
specialization the reason why I push so
hard about this is because if you're if
you're if you're a specialist you have
the opportunity of being a big fish in a
small pond and a big fish in a small
pond is a much better situation than
being a you know a big fish in a big
pond or where she had a small fish in a
big pond so you know and I can give an
example this is an example I use all the
time is that let's say that your garbage
disposal breaks right and you you know
you you look for someone to fix it so
you're going through and you're looking
at plumbers and you see you know ABC
plumbing you see you know Jack's
plumbing and then you see mister garbage
disposal fix-it man plumbing who do you
call right you're more likely to call
missus mr. garbage disposal fix-it man
because he's niched himself down to that
point he's got a really good
specialization you assume that that he's
gonna know the most about fixing garbage
disposals right and and so that's kind
of how I see it in the software
development world is it plus plus and
remember also like who do you think gets
paid more the garbage disposal mister
garbage suppose we'll fix it man
probably charges a premium because of
his name people are going to pay more
for a specialist and so and it's a much
rarer thing right in the in the software
development community if you just wanted
to be you know you think of a famous
software developer like Bob Martin you
know and in fact people use this as a
counter-argument and okay well Bob
Martin is a specialist of of what he's
not a specialist he's a generalist he is
just a well-known software developer you
know you might say agile you might say
you know TDD or something like that but
but he's
some really well-known software
developer now if you want to compete
with him if you want to build a name for
yourself as a well-known software just a
general software developer that's gonna
be really really hard but I'll tell you
what if you pick a really narrowly
defined specialty you know something
like you want to be the the Android
ListView guy or gal right and you know
the most about Android list views are
another one an example C++ pointer guru
you know more about pointers and see if
those posting and they explain them the
intricacies then and now it's better
than anyone else and that's what you
focus on your you can build up a
reputation like people will know who you
are because of that that very narrow
specialty in fact you know if you go to
speak at conferences and you submit a
paper on that and that and you you're
known to be the Android list for you
guys so of course they want to have you
at this this Google Android conference
talking about ListView because you're
the ListView guy or you know whatever it
is I think you're gonna have more of
those opportunities and then you know
where that where you go from this is
that it's concentric circles right so
you start off really really specialized
you build a name for yourself in that
specialization and then you and then you
you find the bigger circle this is where
you expand out and maybe you know if you
get a nice let's say you get a really
solid reputation as the expert on on the
Android ListView control well then you
expand out and you and you use that
reputation to now become well-known in
in Android development and then maybe
you know as you saturate that market is
you're moving to a slightly bigger pond
as you're a bigger fish then then you
could maybe move out to mobile maybe
you're the mobile development person to
a well-known you know celebrity in that
area and then you could expand out to
bigger bigger ponds so it's not like I'm
saying you know I think a lot of people
would misinterpret this and they think
oh John is just saying to specialize in
some super niche area and I'm just gonna
focus on that and I won't know how to do
anything else you know I'm not saying
that I'm saying that you know have a
broad base you can know a lot about
about a lot of things but have your
branding and your marketing and have a
deep knowledge in one specific area to
start with in order to build that
reputation
and then you can branch out from there
but you know you're gonna have a whole
lot of an easier time doing that and
getting paid a lot more if if you do
specialize deeply okay yeah I confess on
somebody who missed the subtlety there I
was assuming that you were talking about
start specialized and stay specialized
but the make a beachhead a special
beachhead and then expand out certainly
makes sense you discuss how to quote
hack the interview quote and I've heard
several different variants on what that
means and to some people it's actually
even kind of very suspicious it's like
if the process could be hacked would I
even want to work for a company like
that what do you mean by that so when I
say hack the interview you know
obviously my my chapter title for in
soft skills is is designed to make
someone go oh you know it might not
accurately is it might not be designed
so much to accurately reflect what what
I'm actually talking about which is I'm
not talking about cheating the interview
right it's not like we're cheating the
interview but what I when I say the word
hack here I'm talking about the way that
you would use hack in terms of like like
life hack right if you're familiar with
the site life hack where we're doing
something that's like a shortcut or
something that's going to you know aid
you or it think about working smarter
that's that's what I'm thinking about
here and so when I'm talking about hack
an interview what I'm actually talking
about is actually avoiding the interview
as much as possible which is basically
you know a lot of developers think that
the interview starts when you show up
and you shake the interviewers hand but
but it starts way before them if you
want to hack the interview process what
you do is you you build a relationship
with the company or the interviewer
ahead of time you get a personal
referral to get in the door because you
know the reality of the situation is
that we're humans right we like to pride
ourselves on the fact that we're
rational beings but we're not rational
we're emotional and that's I mean that's
a core of who we are as human beings as
much as you know as much as we we wish
it weren't
so we don't have crashing aliy you know
plenty of scientific sites just to show
you know that for in psychology but um
but in fact a good book on this would be
a fool by randomness is that's a really
good book that that talks about this but
um but anyway you know we really hire
people that we like and in what we do is
we make up all kinds of justifications
of why they're technically competent why
they're the best candidate and when we
pick the person that we like you know I
I'm I know I'm susceptible to this bias
most of us are you know and we've we've
probably benefited or been hurt by this
in in in the process now this doesn't
mean that you can be a fraud I'm not
saying you know not have any technical
skills obviously if you don't have a
technical skills and you go into an
interview it doesn't matter if the
interviewer likes you you're not gonna
get the job but if you do have skills
you know the best way you know an
interview is not the best way to
determine who's the most qualified
person right in one hour you're not
gonna figure out who is the most
qualified person in one hour you might
figure out who you like so so stack the
deck in your favor
go out and make sure that don't just
cold apply to a job right hacking the
interview is about figuring out how can
you in a smart way you know get get a
personal referral this might if you
don't know someone at that company maybe
you meet someone at that company maybe
you start going to user groups that they
go to maybe you start just you know
connect on LinkedIn and ask to buy a cup
of coffee and maybe you you you figure
out a way to build some relationships or
you follow someone's blog one company
that I got a job at I really wanted to
work at I started following all the
developers blogs and commenting on their
blogs and guess what after it took a
long time but after about three months
every single one of those developers
knew who I was and they liked me because
I like their stuff right and it was I
was genuine I wasn't you know just just
doing this to to to get the job I was
actually like their blogs and I gave
them sincere compliments but but the
idea is that you know you set this up so
that you're coming you're not coming in
cold you're coming in with it with an
invitation someone's giving a personal
referral and even if you can you know
what one I saw this technique and I was
amazed by this technique
a buddy of mine that I'm that that's
running a start-up and I'm an advisor on
that startup he was we were trying to
get into to accelerator programs he want
to get to accelerator programs and we
had some interviews for accelerator
program and he actually emailed the the
people that we were supposed to
interview for the accelerator program
ahead of time and said hey could we meet
like just a five minute I just want to
touch base with you before the interview
like pre-interview you know over Skype
just want to introduce myself and just
chat with you before the interview and I
was like oh like how could this work
like what are you doing they're gonna
say no and all three of them said yes
and they spent about an about a you know
45 minutes an hour talking to us before
the interview and then we walked into
these interviews and we didn't we hardly
had to say a word because this person
that you know that that we had talked to
ahead of time was now pitching us to the
other interviewer to the other
interviewers so there's there's amazing
ways that you can you know build a
relationship ahead of time before that
you know a lot of people walked into the
interview just cold and clammy and and
and trying to make an impression in one
hour
and that's just it's a luck of the draw
at that point so you can really stack
the odds in your favor and that's that's
what I consider hacking the interview
process it's it's not about you know
figuring out you know how to achieve
this system it's about how to how to
make it so that you're able to put your
best foot forward really early on in the
process okay yeah
in my own experience there have been a
lot of times well what happens sometimes
is somebody will ask me for a resume and
I don't actually have one up to date
because I haven't needed one to get jobs
because I have you know I already know
people and have that entry that you're
looking for yep you don't specifically
mention quote networking unquote but
that's a little a lot about what you're
talking about right yeah and it's
interesting you know the reason why I
don't mention the word networking is I
think it gets a bad rap like everyone
mentions networking and
and it's got a bad reputation exactly
because people do it wrong because this
is when people network or this is when I
have people ask me about networking is
when they're looking for a job and
that's not when you network right you
network six months before you're looking
for a job because when you network when
you need something that's not called
networking that's called mooching that's
called you know using people desperately
exactly and people know it right and so
you know you build relationships ahead
of time and that's you want to call that
networking that's what real networking
is it's it's building you know it's
going to it's not just showing up user
groups when you got laid off it's good
you know going to user groups for years
and meeting people and having
connections and giving them value first
right when you come to someone and
you're like hey what can you do for me
can you give me a job can you give me a
referral I you're just at what have you
given give first and then and then ask
you know I think that's where so many
people get networking wrong and that's
why I get such a bad rap it's not
trading business cards it's providing
other people value first and that's
that's how you grow yeah exactly so kind
of shifting gears a bit here to the
section on marketing you know among
engineers marketing is often viewed as a
dark art that's practiced by people who
wear nice suits and shiny shoes and
don't really understand technology how
is marketing relevant to software
developers so you know the thing I think
it comes to is well I mean first like
marketing in general right marketing
exists for a reason marketing is just
simply you know it's got a bad rap but
all it really is is is connecting
someone who needs a product or service
with that product or service right and
as a software developer you provide a
product or you know or service right you
provide code or you can write code so so
there's without marketing no one would
know litters be people that need
something and there'd be people that
have something and no one wouldn't they
wouldn't meet each other they wouldn't
know about it so you have to have
marketing in and really you know as a
software developer the thing is everyone
everyone sells themselves right like
whether you believe it or not whether
you want to or not I mean every time you
go into a meeting with your boss or
coworkers and try to convince them of
your idea that's selling yourself that
is marketing that is salesmanship right
so you can either have this skill that
you really need or or not have the skill
either way you're gonna be judged on
this skill right so you know a lot of
developers say oh I don't want to market
myself I don't want to do that you know
people should respect me for my ability
in my code and the problem is they would
love to do that but they don't know
about it they don't know that you're the
greatest coder in the world that you're
God's gift to to coding because you hit
because there's no evidence of it
because you haven't done any kind of
marketing it's you can have the greatest
product in the world you know I think
you know a lot imagine creating a
startup company today trying to build a
company and not doing any marketing like
you just expect people to come because
you built this awesome thing well you
know I'm an entrepreneur and I know that
that's not true it doesn't happen and
and the same thing is true with us the
software developers and in it even if
you're you know obviously this is true
if you're an entrepreneur you're a
freelancer but just as a career
developer it's very true as well because
if you can market yourself well if you
can if if employers know who you are
right let's imagine you know I'll give
you an example here that I learned this
is why I got so much into marketing cuz
when I first created my blog I didn't
create my blog to market myself I had no
idea I was just expressing my thoughts
and just trying to help and teach people
and you know I had gotten I start
getting emails and eventually I got this
call from a company and and they said
hey John we would we read your blog we'd
like to offer you a position and I said
well oh you mean in an interview so no
no we just want to offer you a job we've
been reading your blog for a while we
all know that you're you know we want to
hire you so you know and I was shocked
right interview that exactly right so so
I start to realize the value that's like
wow this is this is quite powerful
and you can imagine what my negotiating
position would be right if you go and
you apply for a job right and then you
know the employers mmm ha evaluating you
against other people and then they give
you an offer your negotiating position
is it's not the best right you need
something they're giving something if
they come to you and say hey John I want
to hire you specifically can you imagine
how much of a stronger negotiation
position that you're gonna be in and
that in that case and so that's you know
that's really the power of marketing
yourself it just opens up so many
opportunities I mean as I've taught
other developers how to do this and
learn how to do this myself and do it in
a tasteful way I'd like to mention also
here that my what I define marketing is
basically giving people value that's how
I produce a ton of free content my
philosophy is I give you know I give
away 90% of what I do for free and I
charge for 10% of it I make podcasts I
make blog posts I do YouTube videos all
this content I put out there for free
and I charge for first a small portion
of what I do but if you provide enough
people value they're gonna spread your
name they're gonna spread the stuff that
you created and they're gonna they're
gonna see you as valuable and that's the
best way to market it and that's a
tasteful way I think most software
developers that are afraid of marketing
don't like the word marketing I think
you can stomach the idea of giving
people value of helping people and that
in and that is not only is it the most
effective way in the market but it's
also the most tasteful way you're not
gonna have feel like you're you're you
know put join the dark side if you're
giving people value okay so what are
some of the activities you mentioned a
couple like blogging yeah so that that's
where I start most most software
developers
I've actually got a blogging course that
I can I send by email it's totally free
if you just go to simpleprogrammer.com
you can go there and you can sign up
you'll see a pop-up and and you can sign
up for the course but but it's one that
I recommend highly because it's so
accessible there's a
there's sort of a culture around
blogging in the software development
field and and it's extremely effective
it's just you know you just have to be
consistent right um you know I if I go
to conference I'll talk about how to
market yourself we'll do a talk on that
and frequently I'll be in a room with
with several hundred people and I'll say
okay hold up your hand if you if you
have a blog and probably about 50% of
the developers in the room will hold up
their hand I'll say no keep your hand up
if you have blogged in the in the last
month and you know most hands will go
down maybe there's like a quarter left
or last and I'll say okay now keep your
hand up if you've blogged in the last
week and you know almost all the hands
have gone down at this point but maybe
there's a few up they'll say keep your
hand up if you've blocked for the last
the last 52 weeks the last year
consistently once a week at least right
and there be maybe one hand remaining
and usually zero and so if there's one
hand remaining I say congratulations
you're like the point nine nine you know
percent point nine five percent of the
of the developer community as far as
marketing yourself with a blog because
because no one else is doing this so you
know if if you like you can be extremely
effective just by creating a blog and
just by updating it once a week so few
developers do that that you're gonna set
yourself apart in fact you know
considering that I'm doing this at a
conference where those developers are
usually in the top 10% already
I mean imagine how how how much
distinction how much how much more
you're separating yourself away from the
herd if you're if you're doing that if
you're just doing that one simple thing
so along with that you know blogging is
obviously a good first step and being
consistent but you can also you know
obviously like we're doing right now
this podcast people are listening to me
and you and and that's that's a
marketing thing right they're getting
value out of this hopefully and and then
it's also spreading both of our names so
this is this is a good thing marketing
for us right you can create your own
podcast not hard to do right you can
either be on someone else's or create
your own
you can also right
magazine articles maybe you're not gonna
get published in MSDN magazine or I
Triple E on your first try but as you
build up a reputation you can start with
smaller periodicals you can write a book
maybe you're not gonna get a publisher
to to create a book guard to to sign you
on a deal but you can it's so easy to
South publish today it is extremely easy
never been an easier time in history and
then there any any kind of medium that
you consume you can be on so YouTube is
a great one for you know I do a lot of
in front of the camera talking to people
obviously but screencasting on YouTube
like show do tutorials and showing
people how to write code or to solve a
problem excellent way to get exposure
and to market yourself Stack Overflow
open source projects contributing to
them creating them Cora is another good
one today I see a lot of developers
answering questions on Cora so there's
just a ton of different ways out there
to market yourself and to build up a
reputation and brand right yeah you were
talking about tastefully doing this and
something that kind of occurs to me is
that you know most developers object to
marketing because of a bad taste in
their mouth or something like that but
you think about the luminaries or
rockstars that we know you mentioned
Uncle Bob why Bob Martin why do we know
him well because he's done podcasts and
he's done books and he's done blog posts
and he's spoken at conferences all those
kind of things that you're talking about
and even if he wasn't specifically doing
them to market himself that's how we all
know who he is
right yeah yeah it's a good point I mean
it it it can be done in a tasteful way I
think you know a lot of the marketing
that we think of today is it's not good
marketing because it doesn't provide us
value but but I don't know about you but
I like to get like I like to find out
about things that I'm interested in so I
even like to get emails from Apple
telling me about a you know a Mac
upgrade or whatever you know that the
new stuff because I'm excited about that
stuff and and so you know I think a lot
of people don't realize that when you're
providing value to people they're
excited they want to read your new blog
posts they want to hear about this go
ahead and tweet it and on Twitter and
share it on Facebook because people want
to read the stuff if it's providing them
value sure just to play devil's advocate
here you know if I look at you and what
you're doing right now I see you're
doing all kinds of marketing but I don't
see how you would have any time left
over for programming so how would you
answer the developer says well I don't
want to do those things because they
take away from program yeah so that's a
that's a great point so I I wish I had
some more time for programming I've sort
of had to you know my business and my
business model is around teaching
developers soft skills and marketing
themselves and so so that's where my
focus is but it wasn't always there
right you know I built my reputation
just like I talked about specialization
right from a smaller pond and then went
to a bigger pond and and now you know as
much as I love coding and I love
programming it doesn't make sense for me
to to spend my time doing that because I
have a greater effect and can reach more
people by by doing what I'm doing and in
a lab that is teaching developers how to
mark themselves but it doesn't require
that much effort to to have that much of
a fact right so I'm building an entire
business based around this so I spend my
time doing this in fact we you know to
be honest with you once you have this
going right I
I currently I'm currently in Europe and
I've been here for like two two and a
half months I'm on a three-month trip
and I'm I'm working one day a week every
Friday is my work day so I'm actually
doing all this in one day so it's
actually not requiring even even that
much even when it's my whole business so
you know most developers I think you
know if you if you just write one blog
post a week how how much is that effort
is that going to take you it's not going
to take you a huge amount of effort and
you can have it automatically go out on
Twitter and Facebook when you when you
publish it if you step it up and write a
couple of blog posts a week even then
you're gonna have a huge return on your
investment there in about a year we're
the time so it doesn't take a huge
amount to do that now if you want to
become a super famous software developer
you're it's gonna take work it's gonna
take a lot of work and hard work and
yeah I'm not gonna lie about that but
not everyone needs that just having you
know just a lot of the students that
have worked with me that I've have taken
bought my course on how to market
yourself they've basically you know
started out maybe they're doing
freelancing and they're billing $75 an
hour and with just creating a blog and
doing a few of the things that I'm
helping them do they've been able to
raise their hourly rate to $150 $200 an
hour that's a huge difference you know
for the small amount of effort so so
there's still a lot that you can do with
with a little bit you know it doesn't
have to be a full-time thing I would say
that if you if you spent 10% of your
your work time mark working on marketing
type of activities branding building
your brand and building your reputation
that would be enough to have a very big
impact on your career okay so perhaps
maybe it's appropriate to think about it
in terms of investing in yourself
exactly in it and it truly is and you
know it's good that you use that word
because this isn't gonna happen in in a
week it's not gonna happen in three
months you're talking about a minimum
investment of about a year about a year
of being kind of consistently doing this
and working towards this you'll start to
see some traction but but you got to be
consistent you know you got to be able
to to see this as an investment not
something that you just do and
immediately get results so yeah
following up on that what if someone is
in a situation where they would like to
get a new position in the next 30 or 60
days you know we talked before about you
know not going out and quote networking
unquote like say give me a job and you
know you were just now talking about the
length of time to make this investment
are there any quick win kind of tips
that you might have yeah
I think some of them look a lot like the
long-term investments as well because
they'll they'll still pay off they just
won't pay off as well so the very first
thing that I would do is is hire
professional resume writer to write my
resume a lot of people frown on this to
you and they're like oh that I feel like
I should write my own resume but my
answer to that is always the CEO of your
company does does he write his own code
or she write her own code so they hired
you to write code because their time
it's because they're not an expert at
writing code unless they are right sure
they might be able to hack out some
JavaScript and figure it out but you're
the expert so why do you as a software
developer think that you should write a
resume are you a professional resume
writer do you even have you even written
more than five in your whole life those
people have written hundreds or
thousands of them hire professional to
do that thing and that's and you're
gonna get a much better result so that's
that's a really good and I've done this
myself my I've had my wife do this I've
helped I've helped tons of software
developers dozens of soft developers to
get a resume writer to write their
resume and seen tremendous results on
that it makes a huge huge difference
just just uh you know a resume is an is
an ad for yourself it's a one you know
it's a one page or two page ad a lot of
companies it's the only thing they'll
ever see of you you know you think about
it you know when you see an ad in a
magazine or brochure it should it should
pop it should be effective it should
convey the information about of time so
that can make a huge huge impact on
getting another job or getting a
promotion it's having a very good
well-run resume and it doesn't mean that
you don't have to do any work you
provide the resume writer with all the
details in the information and then
they're gonna format it and package it
in a way that's going to present nicer
that's going to highlight your strong
points that's going to you know pop
that's gonna be a good advertisement for
you so that's number one
I would say and then number two I would
go default right back to blogging even
you know I if I were looking for a job
for the next 30 to 60 days I would blog
three times a week
I would try to get a blog up start
blogging three times but just short you
know maybe 500 2000 word posts you know
small things just so that you get a nice
good volume in there so that when you go
into an interview because before you go
into the interview right let's say I'm
interviewing someone what's the first
thing that I'm gonna do well let's see
let's see Joe let me let me type your
name into Google right that's what
that's what pretty much every interview
I guarantee you is going to do and
they're gonna type your name into Google
and see what comes up and if your blog
comes up or if you have it on your
resume they're gonna click that and
they're gonna look through it and
they're gonna see when was the last time
you updated your blog and they're gonna
see what you wrote and and if it's
interesting and there's a lot of content
there they're gonna be pretty impressed
probably so um so so that's that can be
effective you know it's not gonna get
it's not gonna do what I call inbound
marketing right if you blog for 60 days
people aren't chances of people finding
you is low right so people aren't gonna
come after you that's gonna take a year
or more but it's it's good for outbound
marketing if you have a blog and you've
got a lot of articles on there that
you've written in the last 60 days and
you send that out there or you're
already going in for an interview that's
gonna be really helpful so I'd say that
those are the two main activities
obviously in a 60-day time window you
can also start showing up at user groups
and not pushing right just showing up
just showing up is enough so I would
probably do that and yeah I would also
probably invest in a nice nice suit you
know in most places that's going to help
your your chances and and yeah I think
that's that's probably you know you
could probably make some connections at
a company and that time as well
especially if you know someone who knows
someone and again at that short time
window you want to make sure that you
don't do high pressure type of of
networking you want to just meet people
and just if you if you're there some way
you can provide them value no strings
attached that's always good as well okay
yeah I like that distinction between
inwa inbound and outbound
and marketing for your blog and so in
the if you're trying to do something
quick it's gonna be outbound sort of
thing but typically you're talking about
blogging as an inbound thing so that
people can discover you or rather than
you going out and looking for that
exactly yep oh great so we've covered
the sections on career and marketing
yourself what do you think the most the
next most important section in your book
is for developers I would probably say
productivity it's hard between that and
and learning in mindset you know the
spirit side but productivity like you
know having a good productivity system
in understanding how to be productive
can overcome a lot of obstacles I think
you know what when you look at a lot of
people stay they you know honestly look
at it you might be effective like your
total effectiveness might be like one or
two hours on average of actually
producing stuff and that can be tripled
fairly easily with with a good system
and scheduling and and time tracking and
if you can get to the point where you're
producing three times the output that
you were before or sometimes four times
the output you're gonna be able to be a
lot more effective even if you're doing
things the wrong way that that that
level of output so so that's where where
I would say is probably that the next
important section and I give my entire
process I've got a a system that I've
developed that I plan my week out I use
sort of a combination of the Pomodoro
Technique which is this technique where
you you set a 20 minute timer and you
you work on one task focus and they take
a five minute break but but I I planned
that out on on a Kanban board and I go
over that entire system I also use what
I call a quota system as well and and I
give some of my productivity kind of
techniques and hacks that can can help
you to be productive and these were the
things that I use that you know I think
I think I talked about it in the book
but in in one year I had used these
techniques to produce 30 fulling you
know five
our long Pluralsight courses produce 52
blog posts I think something like 30
YouTube videos and and produce two
podcasts all like within one year time
period plus plus doing hourly consulting
and hitting the gym and running you know
three times a week so I was able to be
extremely productive using those
productivity techniques and that's and I
don't hold anything back it's it's all
in the book so yeah I think I saw a blog
post of yours on that before I even got
to that chapter on the book and I liked
it because it showed how to kind of put
the pieces together of Pomodoro
Technique plus Kanban or whatever you
want to call it I found that interesting
so as we're kind of wrapping things up
here how can people find out more about
you and follow your activities I'll
include links to everything so you don't
have to spell things out okay so I
definitely I mean the easiest might hub
is that simpleprogrammer.com and you
know from there you can find everything
I've got you know obviously if you're
interested in marketing yourself I sell
a course with with books on how to
market yourself a software developer at
dev career boosts calm and and then I've
got a YouTube channel which has totally
free YouTube videos I do three videos a
week my blog has you know content coming
out every pretty much every day now and
then I've got a podcast called get up in
code it's just about fitness for
programmers and then one called entre
programmers which is for entrepreneur
developer Newars
and then another one which is the simple
programmer podcast which is basically
Q&A type of questions that i've answered
that are sort of the same type of things
from the YouTube video and then and then
interviews but but yeah so that's it
it's all you can find a hole at
simpleprogrammer.com
so that's kind of a portal to John's
world yep pretty much okay okay well
John thanks for being on the show yeah
thank you it was a great great great to
be here great great questions Thanks
this is Charles Anderson for software
engineer and radio thanks for listening
[Music]
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio - to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on iTunes
mention a message us on Twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team @ SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Applause]
[Music]
you